All right, I am admitting everybody from
the lobby. Uh recording for this meeting
has started. Good morning everybody.
We'll give just a minute or so for
everybody who is in the lobby to enter
into the main room. In the meantime, my
name is Dominic Zerlo. I am the director
for the center for medical cannabis and
psilocybin at the department of health
and this is the dosage administration
and clinical practice committee meeting
with the chair Ian Dunn. Uh and so thank
you everybody for being here and at this
time I will turn it over to Ian. The
meeting is yours Ian.
>> Perfect. Well good morning everyone. Uh
my name is Ian Dunn. I'm the chair of
the medical psilocybin advisory board
but as well as the dosage administration
and clinical practice committee. Um
today is uh we are going to be going
over those preparation documents that
we've been working on the last couple of
meetings. Um probably uh formal adoption
if there are no new objections and then
we will begin reviewing administration
sessions um and looking at just the
preliminary details what we want to see.
This is the beginning of the editing
journey. Definitely not as finalized as
that preparation one. So, just a
reminder to everyone in case uh someone
is new or they haven't been here before.
What are committees? Committees operate
in in an advisory capacity. Um they
provide a forum for individuals who may
be experts but may not serve on the
board due to real or perceived conflicts
of interest. Committees support the
board by expanding community input,
incorporating subject matter expertise,
and increasing participation in program
development. I will now turn over to
introductions. So if you would like to
share your name, your role of area of
expertise, um and your perspective or
interest related to dosage
administration and clinical practice,
that would be greatly appreciated. At
this time, I'll turn over to Johnny to
call the hands.
>> All right. And um yeah, if you want to
raise your hand um uh to speak, uh
there's a icon at the top banner with a
hand that says raise. Um, and you can
also drop that in the chat as well if
you would prefer to do that.
All right. And I see the first hand up,
we've got Kate Hawk. And Kate, I've
allowed your mic and you can unmute.
>> Yeah. Good morning everyone. This is
Kate Hawk from Santa Fe. And um if I
guess what's relevant here is I've been
a a psychedelic assisted therapy
facilitator for some decades and happy
with to be concluded in this process.
Thanks.
>> Awesome. Thanks Kate. And we've got
James Brown in the chat. Morning
everyone. James Brown Pharma D. Happy to
be here today.
Right. And I see Katherine Waro's hand.
And Katherine, your mic is enabled.
>> Good morning, everybody. Um, just always
grateful for everybody that shows up and
is willing to dedicate time to this. Um,
I am located in Los Cusus. I am a
licensed professional counselor with
private practice. Really excited about
all the work everybody's doing. So,
thank you for being here.
>> Awesome. Thanks, Katherine.
All righty. I see no other hands. So, um
if you would like to participate later,
um and you haven't introduced yourself,
just go ahead and um either post it in
the chat or just let us know before you
start speaking. Hey, I'm this person. Um
and that would be greatly appreciated.
So now let's go ahead and go over to the
preparation session document that we
have been working through um as a
committee.
[clears throat]
Perfect.
So um it begins with psycho
psychological preparation. So that's
going to be um done by the psychedelic
therapist.
And here's it in chat. Psychedelic
therapist. Um it's the phase that occurs
first. It's also the phase where we look
at medical history, intention setting
and objectives, the orientation to set
um clinical safety planning matrix, uh
general education on who, what, where,
who, what, why, and how of psilocybin
and potential adverse effects, dosing
and tearing, referral, cultural and
spiritual alignment, and then
determination of readiness. And this is
what's being done by the psychedelic
therapist in regards to preparation. um
the facilitator who is not a licensed
professional. They are um they are
licensed by the department but they do
not hold a separate license like a
social worker or clinical counselor that
kind of thing. Um so this final
preparation session must be conducted by
the facilitator who will be present
during the administration session. So
they are responsible for obtaining that
informed consent that final saying hey
like you are going to be taking a
substance um making sure that the
facilitator is the correct fit you know
that their personalities work together
um and are compatible the logistics and
boundaries so that's touch preferences
written disclosures and orienting the
patient to the nonclinical scope of the
facilitator um it also includes
establishing boundaries
[clears throat and cough] so we had set
in the other um preparation. In this
one, we have setting. We want them to
orient the patient to the physical
environment where the session will
occur. So, the healing center or
approved location um making sure that
the lighting, the temperature, the
sound, um privacy measures, uh and
ensuring the patient is comfortable with
the facility layout. Um the facilitator
is responsible for knowing how to
escalate medical or psychological
concerns.
Um this should be part of their general
orientation. Uh they also have cultural
and spiritual alignment. They are the
ones to provide the actual materials for
patient self- administration in
accordance with therapist direction. And
um they establish a transportation plan.
So a patient must have a plan for
transportation as they should not drive
for 24 hours post administration of
psilocybin. Um and then if other
modalities are going to be used then the
patient must be notified and agree
otherwise other modalities cannot be
used. And then we have the final section
the combined timing and compliance
standards.
This is going to be um
here is it in chat. This is going to be
the total duration. So they should have
to complete at least two preparation
sessions totaling no less than 3 hours
prior to first admission administration.
So again that's a minimum of one prep uh
psych psychological prep and one
administrative prep. Um at least one
session must be dedicated to
psychological preparation um and one to
administrative where feasible. At least
one hour of total preparation shall be
conducted in person. This is for setting
that um those setting expectations,
those um personality fit expectations.
That's why we kind of say, "Hey, we want
an hour. We want to make sure that this
is a psychedelic therapist and
facilitator that you want to work with."
Um the sequence, so psychological
preparation must be completed and
clinical appropriateness determined
before we ever get to um that setting
and the administrative prep. And then
all activities including clinical
screening results from the therapist and
informed consent from the facilitator
must be documented in the patient
record. So I will now open for any
questions, comments, concerns on what
we've worked through so far.
>> All right. And I see Katherine's hand
first and you can unmute.
>> Yes. Um so after attending the training
um with meeting last week, we started
really talking a lot about groups and
I'm just wondering with prep, what is
that going to look like with individual
versus groups? Like I know we've got in
here that there needs to be, you know,
so many number of sessions. Are those
going to be individ like? So if they're
going to be working in a group scenario,
are all the prep sessions individual?
Are they in a group setting with the
other group members? Like how is that I
guess I'm just want I don't know if
we've even discussed any of this and I
just am wondering if that needs to be
included especially when we're talking
about setting in prep.
um do they need to have been ex like do
they need to know who the other people
are going to be that are there because
that can make a huge difference, right?
Like if for example they don't even know
the people that they're going to be um
dosing within a group and they show up
on the day of and it turns out they know
somebody and they don't like that
person, that's probably something that
should have been worked out um
beforehand. So, I don't know. So I guess
I just wanted to to bring up groups and
how does and and what do we need to be
considering around that with respect to
prep. Thank you. So in my opinion and so
again the the committee is free to
disagree. Um, I think that even for
group that psychological prep, the
intention setting should probably be
personalized and individualized because
even two people with the same conditions
may not have the same goals.
>> I agree.
>> Um,
>> and then that administrative prep where
we're already trying to find the um,
you know, the correct fit, right?
because not every facilitator is going
to be compatible with every patient just
like not every therapist is compatible
with every patient. Um so since they
already have in here correct fit I'll
just include patient facilitator and
group members if applicable.
I do agree. I think intentions and a
most of the prep needs to be done
individually. I just wasn't sure if we
[clears throat] want to make sure to
specify that because you're right, I
think people can get lost in the mix if
we're doing group intentions, right?
That may not satisfy the individual, but
I also think there's a piece of this
group where they need to be exposed to
them. So, I don't know if maybe the the
um admin prep could be done together and
maybe the in the psychological prep
should be done separate. I I I don't
know. I I'm I'm literally still trying
to formulate it all in my my mind, but
um I just thought it warranted some
discussion.
>> Yeah, and I definitely agree those I in
my opinion psych prep, individualized
um and then admin prep. Well, that's
where you're you would be getting used
to the setting, seeing if that was what
you like. Um and then that part we could
also introduce. Okay, here are going to
be your group members. Um, and here are
going to be who's with you. I think one
of the reasons why that hasn't been paid
as much attention here is because the
one of the large um in demand for groups
is end of life care. Um, and I saw that
in the end of life care committee with
their families wanting to be involved.
Um, so in that instance, right, we don't
have to introduce someone new. they all
know each other. But I also recognize
that not every group session is going to
be like that. So I think I would stick
with the psych prep individualized and
admin prep um not but I will defer to
the committee. I also see that Dominic
has his hand up.
>> Yeah. And sorry to sort of jump ahead of
you um Kate. I just wanted to say that I
remember that these are really best
practices and maybe the way to do that
is to put just a note in there Ian about
that at some point at the discretion of
the uh the therapist and in the therapy
therapeutic environment for the
preparation. There should be a point
where those people who are going through
a group meet prior to the journey
itself. But let that determination of
exactly when be something that the
therapeutic and the patient sort of
millu that they determine among
themselves. If that makes sense because
it could be in some at some times with
certain people having that introduction
earlier in the preparatory period is
going to be more important and for
others it may be a little bit later. Um
and so I think maybe that would be the
way to go around that is to just ensure
that some point during that preparatory
phase there is uh a meeting of the group
if that makes sense.
>> Yeah. And then under the combined timing
I do have at least one hour of total
preparation time shall be conducted in
person. So I think I can add if
doing a group session
then this time should be used to
introduce
group
participants.
I also think it is going to be important
in the psychological prep that we spell
out that those need to be done
individually because I could see some
people just wanting to do group from
start to finish and I don't think that
serves the clients as well the patients
as well.
Oh okay. This should be done
um
individual. This should be
individualized
to patients.
There should not be group
intention settings. for instance.
>> I think the same will be true for
integration. Um I think actually I think
integration might be we might want to do
a group and an individual but I know
that's later so we're focused on prep
right now. Yeah.
>> All right. And I mean a lot of this
stuff right I we wouldn't want done
as a group anyway. Like we're not
looking at like group medical history.
That would be kind of embarrassing. they
just like are in a circle and you're
like actually
>> yeah. [laughter]
>> Um so yeah, I definitely agree. But Kate
has had her hand up for a really long
time, so I want to I want to give her a
chance to speak.
>> Well, thank you. I am so glad we're
having a little time to look this
through and Katherine's points about
group work are really important and what
Dominic said and we are coming up
against once more what's minimum
requirements for everybody and what's
best practices that can be you know
personalized and according to uh the
expertise that is dealing with the real
situation. Uh well so a number of things
uh I agree that there should be
individual prep psychological prep um I
don't think that it's necessarily a bad
thing to share intentions as a group um
most recently you know I was working
with a group of veterans in the FDA
phase one mushroom study and it was
really important the group they had
individual prep and then I mean all this
was done in the week of the um of the
dosing session and none of it was called
therapy. So that was that model for
research which isn't necessarily what we
were talking about. But even then they
had an individual prep session and then
they had a group prep session where they
shared quite a bit including you know
history and intentions and um so I would
you know I would leave out that um we're
discouraging sharing of intentions may
may be appropriate in some places or
not.
So there's just one point
trying to think of anything else related
to groups because you know there's a
difference I think between are we
looking at this whole experience for a
group like a group of veterans or like a
family or is it more like being
efficient and costeffective where we
group people together who may not stay
in touch afterwards. Uh and so you know
we're there both of those things are
going to happen. So um we're just
looking at the minimal requirements.
>> Yeah. And to kind of piggyback off of
that, right, that will be up to the the
individual approved healing centers to
run their group sessions. So we are
going to see you know some where it is
like families and people that have known
each other or are going to stay in
contact or build that friendship and um
companionship but there are going to be
others right that are just trying to
make a profit. So I think we have to
make
hope for the best prepare for the worst
in terms of what we're going to see. And
I think these are pretty solid um
outline I do want to address. So I
didn't mean to like say no group
intention sharing. I just wanted like
each individualized person to set their
intention and then as a group like they
can share or they can cuz I don't know I
can't say specifically what is going to
go on in the um correct fit session
where they're seeing if the group
members and the patient and the
facilitator are just uh compatible. Um
so I don't know what's going to happen
in that session or how they're figuring
that out. Maybe it is sharing um you
know their
I can't think of the word um what they
talked about their intention and so
maybe it is sharing that maybe it's some
other method I'm not speaking on that
specifically but I think if we are I
just wanted them to you know not be
pressured and say okay you have to pick
your intention match the group and Maybe
I did not say that correctly, but thank
you again. Uh, James,
>> oh, I've got a few other things.
We can we can come back to it, but just
to wrap up this one, I think, yeah, a
lot of these things will be left up to
the professionals or the qualified
people on the on on the ground. Uh I
think in general as far as principles it
it's like at least one individual
preparation session and then also the
idea that there won't be any surprises
like no new people introduced right at
the dosing day.
>> So just aligning that with that and um
we can come back to me if other people
have something urgent. I just got other
other points on the whole document.
>> Yeah. No worries. Uh, James,
>> morning everyone and uh, of course,
Katherine and I really appreciate
Catherine bringing this up and Kate, you
can talk as much as you need. You're
the big things is I think we're missing
in a group setting and I'm so happy we
talked about this today right now is
confidentiality. I what we do is we have
them sign a confidentiality agreement
that we haven't discussed yet. And so I
think that's something that we need to
have somewhere as a best practice is
that agreement
because a lot's going to be shared. A
lot's going to happen in those groups.
It's it can be very amazing, but some
things can also come out where people
don't want to sh don't want that out
there. And so in a group, you have to
have that confidentiality agreement
signed um prior to the actual session.
And so we usually do that uh during that
preparation phase. That's when we'll
bring in that confidentiality agreement
and say here you go. It's just one other
thing. It's not a cons. It's different
than consent and but we in a groups make
them do that. It doesn't we don't do it
with individuality. Uh but we do it with
group settings. And I think that's
important to to somehow put that best
practice as well as again I think you
guys are hitting it on the the nail on
the head here is is that individuality
in groups. What we do is we
individualize them but also it's in a
way there's two different kind of
there's multiple theories out there I
don't want to say two there's a lot of
of theories like so let's say we are
having a group and there's we're laying
down in mattresses that's that's very
common or in beds type of style and
they're all laid out together either in
a circle a singular line whatever they
feel like they want to orientate
themselves as and then when they're
there we have it sounds like posty notes
we have these posty notes that go on and
that allows the facilitator and the
other people to kind of understand and
remember this person's intentions and so
I just you know as a best practice it's
kind of a neat thing to see as as we
evolve you know it's kind of like an FYI
reminder like when you go up to somebody
you're like oh hey they're really
intentioning this now again that's their
session and what they're going through
and what they need to heal on um and so
we really make sure that we're using
that non-bias approach and we're using
that intention that they've set
throughout their journey and experience.
I think that's important that we
continue to
let them fully experience what they're
going to go through and not us imposing
those things on them again. And uh and
we do that in the group by by having
those like little posty notes kind of by
them in the group settings because
there's so many people sometimes you'll
forget or you'll not know the specifics
and so it's just important to reminders
again. So we I think we need a
confidentiality agreement and we need to
just remind ourselves that individuality
in group is so key but group intention
is also key and and and we do let
everybody know not everybody's
intentions personally but the overall
intention is is this and then in and
then we set individuals. Thank you so
much.
>> Thank you. So I went ahead and added um
under the informed consent uh if
participating in a group session they
must sign a confidentiality form. Um and
then in terms of the intention like
sticky notes or individualization that
would either we can add it later in the
administration session cuz this is just
about collecting that information. if we
want to like say like we have to
individualize and do that that would be
more in um administration
for what they do in that regard but um
otherwise
I agree with
the large part of what you're saying. I
don't want to say all because it was a
little fast and my brain is not fully
woken up yet. But um
yeah, I believe I covered Did I miss
something, James?
No. Ian, you're right. Uh and the
posting note was just a just a best
practice that we kind of do. I don't
necessarily think I just was sharing
with you guys kind of a a just a group
experience
>> and I can definitely see that. And
especially when um the patients that
I've seen or been around undergoing
psilocybin therapy um it is a very
I don't want to say like
but very like antagrate amnesia in the
terms of they don't remember what they
did right before often times is what
I've seen and so if a little reminder of
like where they are on their journey
where the final
and gay is um
could be immensely helpful. I could
definitely see that. Um Katherine,
>> yeah, just to kind of share a little bit
about the way I do it. I actually am
working with clients to prepare their
intentions, you know, multiple sessions
in advance. And I even ask them to write
write it out and bring it and they have
it next to them during their session.
So, it's, you know, anywhere from 3 to
10 intentions. Um, and then we're we're
literally reading them their their
intentions during their sessions. As
they go to the restroom, when they come
back, we will ask them, "Would you like
one of your intentions?" If they say
yes, then we'll just read one to them.
So, we're giving them back their own
words. We're not like giving them our
own words. But I also feel that if
preparation is done right um and well,
the intentions are locked and loaded by
the time the client is ready to journey.
Like I can't tell you how many times
I've you know was about to give somebody
an intention and they're like, "Oh, I
already did them all." Like they're
already done. [laughter] And I'm like,
"Awesome. Well, then enjoy the rest of
your your trip." Um but you know, I
think that I think it is important. I
like I like what James is saying is that
he's trying to make sure that we're
giving them what they created, not what
we think they need. Right? So So however
we want to put that, I think that's
what's really important is that we're
not telling them what they need to be
doing on their journey. We're honoring
what their journey is doing for them for
them and what they pre-prepared with
their what they're, you know, wanting to
like highlight or focus on. So, thank
you.
>> Yes, thank you. Um, so I have reposted
with the edits in the chat. Um, if
anyone else has a question, comment,
concern or thing I still haven't
addressed. If you have brought something
up and I have not, uh, Kate
Oh, Kate, I think um your mic is enabled
if you're able to unmute.
>> Oh, thank you. That helps. Yeah. Um a
couple of things. Uh, one is those of us
who've been involved with this
understand that we're talking about
people with existing licenses being the
psychedelic therapist role. Uh, not
requiring that to have flexibility for
qualified people who could do the
facilitators role. Um, and that often
this may be the same person. Right? So
I'm just wondering if in the document
that could be clarified that yes these
are different hats to be put on and
people could be one or the other but
also um you know likely to be both.
Yeah. Uh so in it's not in this document
but it is in a document that this
committee approved um the actual roles
for clinical role uh psychedelic
therapists and facilitators
um and the clinician and the
practitioner were
written written and explicitly say like
a person can hold multiple lensures as
long as they um meet the qualifications
of those individual ones. So, it doesn't
need to be here, but it definitely um is
already considered and in the
definitions of these roles, we say um
hey, this can be the same person.
>> Okay, good. I just know that question
comes up, but um [clears throat] if it's
clarified in the whole system, that's
good. In the introduction today, um, you
said like the facilitator is licensed by
the department. Is license the actual
word or is it more some kind of a permit
or is it actually going to be called
licensed?
>> Certified license approve I don't know
what they want to use. Um,
[clears throat]
>> actually by statute it's permit but you
know it it this is one of those where
it's a semantics issue. Um, so it'll
still have the same sort of, you know,
weight, so to speak. It's just that the
terms that we have to use for this is
going to be permit. And that's actually
true in for all of the different
practitioners,
>> right?
>> Good. I got it. Trying to get this all
the sematics
straight too though. But but the other
the psychedelic therapists do actually
have to be licensed people, you know,
already. they they have to have a
lensure in a therapeutic field. Correct.
Right. And that's actually in a way that
helps to distinguish that someone has
that lensure and then the department is
permitting them. So at least that's the
way I try to think of it.
>> Yeah, that's been my understanding. Just
want to make sure it's it's all clear.
Okay. So little bitty things. Um, in
this document there were some places
where it says should and I was wondering
is there actual flexibility there or do
we really mean you know they will or
must do it? I could point something out
if I was looking at it, but there was a
couple of spots.
Ian, you're on mute. You've been on
mute. Ian, you're on mute.
>> I am so sorry everyone. I was talking to
myself apparently. Um, [laughter] I went
through the document and controlf and
change them all to shell. It It's just
that they're synonymous in my head and I
know that they're not synonymous and
like technical jargon, but
[clears throat] they updated.
>> Thanks. I I figure this is the time to
be picky. So, um, okay. And let's see
what else. Oh, there's one about a
referral to the primary care provider.
This was these are notes from earlier
when I was just looking at the document.
Um,
we could find that cuz I I
was just wondering it's like well we're
not likely to be referring them back to
their primary care provider who's not
who doesn't have the expertise in this
there right there. Yes.
>> Yes. So um if the reason we have this is
for um our inqualified patients. So for
instance, we don't say like if you have
hypertension, you can't
participate, but we do say if you have
clinically uncontrolled hypertension, so
you're not taking any action to try to
prevent organ damage. That's when we're
like, "Okay, got it.
>> We need them to either refer to their
primary care so that they can get the
blood pressure treatment or we'll have
to find another avenue cuz I don't want
to give transient hypertension to
someone who already has um hypertension.
That would be probably not very fun to
be their kidneys,
>> right?" No, that actually does make
sense. We're talking about clinically
inappropriate, sort of like medically
inappropriate.
>> Yeah. there. Okay. Um and there was
something about readiness.
Uh
talking about
So readiness um is the psychedelic
therapist um she's done all of the
psychedelic prep work with um this
patient. And so she's saying or he or
she is saying that
that
do they need more psychological
preparation? Are they going to be okay?
Do do you feel confident? Basically,
it's the psychedelic therapist saying, I
feel confident that they are
psychologically ready.
>> I got that. So, okay. So, this if they
need an additional psychological
preparation, so we're just kind of
breaking it down to the psychological
part or the medical and physical part.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Okay, that actually makes sense.
Um, and then on the on the final
preparation within 30 days, that seems
like a long time. Like things could
change and people could maybe not really
remember everything that they'd talked
about if it's within 30 days. And I know
we want to have flexibility, but um, you
know, I would just hope that it could be
done like more maybe within a week or
two.
Yeah. So, um why did we do 30 days?
It was
I can't remember the discussion. Um I
know it was originally 60 days because
we were following Oregon. We halfed it
to 30. We could do it again to two
weeks. My concern is um
number of beds in the beginning. Um, I
don't know how many patients. It's
really hard to try to
find a statistically relevant sample
that of which we could
infer, but um that's my biggest concern.
Would you like to do
14?
Well, I mean, I'd like to hear what
everybody thinks on that. If it were
just up to me, I'd say that. But I', you
know, I'm open to
>> Yeah. Let's hear from the committee.
Does it is is everyone okay with 14 days
or would you prefer 30?
>> Ian, this is I just want to say that I
some of what I recall too is folks folks
[clears throat] who also live in rural
and frontier areas that um 14 days may
not be enough and as far as
transportation. So, uh, I just wanted to
bring that up as part of the
conversation. I recall that 14 days was
enough. Uh, but 60 days was too much.
Uh, so that's that's what I just wanted
to add in there without recall help
folks recall that.
>> Thank you.
>> I see Katherine's hand up and Katherine,
you can unmute.
>> So, I would say, you know, I I I kind of
agree that 30 days is a lot. I mean, I'm
kind of thinking maybe split the
difference to three weeks. Um, maybe we
could also do like 14 days unless there
are certain, you know, unless there's
extenduating circumstances, like
something like that. I I don't know. But
I I remember when we talked about it
last time, and I thought 30 days was a
long time, too. But I do remember that
60 days to me was no way. That's way way
too long. So, I don't know. I'm thinking
two to three weeks makes sense.
hearing that I think
>> I would say let's just hard cap it at
three weeks. That way we don't have to
do a two week and then extenduating
circumstances in my opinion. But I will
let James
>> Ian and and Katherine everybody I think
you're you're 100% right. The sooner the
better is always the best practice on
this stuff. We always want to try to do
it this as close as possible. Um but
again, you know, looking at regulations,
this is a best practice type of
document. 3 weeks makes sense. 21 days
and then we can always ratchet later
makes sense. We can always dial it if
we're finding out that that's too far.
The data is coming in, it's not showing
positive, as positive as we want. Um and
we can say, hey, now it's 14 days. That
make sense? I I like that little bit of
flexibility so we're not too too strict,
but also with the thought process of
sooner the better. Thank you.
>> Yeah, you know just looking at this this
is
we want to have flexibility and along
with best practices and in the training
we can have more of a discussion about
what's ideal and here we want to have um
as much flexibility as is reasonably
possible.
All right. So, I went ahead and updated
um so the session must occur no less
than 12 hours and no more than 21 days
before administration.
Um the committee recommends the sooner
the better for prep to admin.
>> Yeah, while we're on that that you know
12 hours and maybe we do want to give it
uh that much flexibility but also I
think ideally we want people to have a
chance to think things over if it's you
know if if there's still a chance to say
oh this doesn't feel right. It's hard to
change things when oh it's going to
happen tomorrow. Um but just wanted to
make a comment on that that ideally I
think you know at least give people a
day to think about it but uh we can we
can live with whatever it says here and
then u aim for better practices in in
practice.
I just find that like a night I think
that's what we talked about last time is
a night's sleep, right? Because I
usually do the last session the evening
before [snorts] or the afternoon before
so that they because they should be
mostly ready to go. They're just making
sure they're getting to see everything,
right? Um, and I because for me it's all
about nothing new on the day of, which I
think Kate you mentioned that I think
that's really critical. Um, I think
before it was 24 hours
and I think it was like but then that
would mean really two days before
because you have to have so like if we
were going to be dosing
I think I just wonder about weekends,
right? Like if you're trying to do this
on a Monday,
if especially if if people have to
travel now, they have to wait 24 hours.
So it's almost like, how do I say this?
They have to come for two nights before
instead of one night before if they're
far away
if it's 24 hours versus 12 hours. That's
just my two cents.
>> Yeah. And I mean, I could be fine with
12 hours. Just wanted to say that. And
then I do also want to add that we have
a total of 3 hours of preparation
um with one of those being preferred to
be in person. Obviously we are a very
large geographical state so not always
possible but um in that right it's not
like we're saying we're just saying 12
hours from the last
part before you can start. but they've
realistically been going through all of
their psychological prep um and doing a
lot of that stuff. So, they're prepared
and have had time to kind of make those
decisions. This is just the final saying
like, "Okay, do you want us to get do
you want us to order the supplies or
are you
not okay with this?" And so, I like the
you get to sleep on it personally.
That's what we often tell people. Um,
before you make a major decision, just
sleep on it. Um, but I'm open to
whatever the committee feels.
>> Okay. I'm I'm good with everything.
Thank you.
>> All right. Any other questions,
comments, concerns?
And then I see Don Moser, your mic has
been enabled.
And to to unmute, Don, you'll want to
find the mic icon um and click that.
Yeah, there you go.
>> I got it. Ben, I'm new to all of this.
So, my question regards [clears throat]
how how groups are formed. Are they
brought together by
professionals or is there a limitation
to the group size?
Just uh some kind of basic questions.
>> So
it would not be our place to regulate
what each in individual institution that
um ends up offering group services does.
Um I can imagine a couple different
scenarios. For instance, like um a
person going through end of life
treatment might uh similarly go through
a psy a psilocybin treatment as well to
deal with that existential distress. Um
and so that group wouldn't be picked by
professionals. It was just your family.
Um but there are also talks of like well
group sessions for economic reasons and
those ones probably would be paired by a
professional. So it depends on the
institution once the program is fully
off the ground to decide um how that is
going to be executed.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Of course.
>> All righty. Any other questions,
comments, concerns before we go ahead
and move to a vote on this.
All righty. At this time, if you are in
favor of adopting the preparation
sessions as posted in the chat, please
raise your hand.
Do you see four hands here? Five,
including your own.
>> Yeah, perfect. Please to lower your
hands at this time.
All of those opposed, please raise your
hand at this time.
And I do not see any hands.
>> With a vote of five to zero, the
preparation sessions document is adopted
and we can get moving on to
administrative sessions.
15.
>> Okay.
So, this one I broke into um a bunch of
little modules essentially, and it's all
of the different kind of parts that one
brain could consider. Um so, I'm going
to definitely need y'all's help, but it
starts with um administration sessions
involve the supervised facilitation of a
patient's medical psilocybin experience
within an approved setting. So they
serve to provide a safe and supportive
environment, maintain patient physical
and psychological safety, uh support the
patient during altered states of
consciousness, monitor physiological and
psychological responses during
administration, ensure compliance with
regulatory and facility safety
requirements, and facilitate a
therapeutic environment conducive to
introspection, emotional processing, and
insight. and administration sessions
occur after completion of required
preparation sessions and prior to post
session integration.
All right, basically a lot of fun words
to say this happens after preparation
but before integration.
Administrations must meet the following
minimum requirements. So this is going
to be the part we are going to first
discuss. Um administration must occur
within an approved setting. Not our
choice, that's the law. But the
facilitator must be present and
available to provide support during the
duration of the administration session.
Um administration must be documented in
the patients clinical record and
administration sessions must comply with
all applicable state regulations,
facility policies and safety protocols.
Questions, comments, concerns on minimum
administration requirements.
Perfect. All righty. Informed consent
confirmation. So, prior to
administration, facilitators must
reconfirm informed consent through
direct discussion with the patient. This
discussion must include confirmation
that the patient understands the nature
of psilocybin administration, potential
psychological and physical effects, the
possible intensity or unpredictability
of the experience, and the patient's
right to pause or terminate the session
at any time. Consent and confirmation
must be documented prior to
administration.
All right. Any questions, comments,
concerns on the informed consent
confirmation?
>> Katherine, morning.
>> Yeah, just curious a little bit about
the patients right to pause or terminate
the session at any time.
Have we discussed what happens if
they're in the middle of it and they're
like, I'm out. Like, we can't let them
just leave, right? So [laughter]
what what does that mean and what does
that look like?
>> I was meaning it up until
administration.
>> Um
>> so we may need to rewrite the language
on that.
>> So maybe to schedule re something about
scheduling the session is what I'm
hearing you say,
>> right? To postpone,
>> cancel, postpone, right?
So patients right to postpone, cancel or
delay a session at any time before
administration.
>> That's much better. Thank you. Mhm.
And then uh consent confirmation must be
documented prior to administration.
All right. Dosage and admin. Oh, we have
a few more hands. So, sorry about that,
Kate. Oh, Dominic was first. Sorry about
that. Yeah, the only thing I wanted to
add is it we just need to make sure that
the patient confidentiality is included
in the
>> in the informed consent.
All right. And then I see Kate Hawk.
>> Yeah. Would it be appropriate to put uh
whatever the consent regarding touch is
in this section?
Uh so we collected the touch consider
consent um during psychological prep.
Did you want us to like reaffirm it?
>> Yeah, that's generally good practice, I
think.
And I'm just going to say reaffirm
boundaries because we referred to
boundaries in the previous document as
um
where was it?
Includes establishing boundaries such as
touch reference, providing written
disclosures or orienting the patient to
the nonclinical scope of the
facilitator. So reaffirm boundaries with
the patient before administration.
Um, all right. And then we had James.
Oh, sorry. Did you have something else?
>> No, I just said Okay, that's good.
>> Perfect. Thank you. Uh, James Brown,
Dominic, right here, I think we, uh, and
Ian, I think right here, we need the
patient bill of rights. We kind of
talked about that last time. Again, it's
a little different than the
confidentiality. It's called the patient
bill of rights that we use. Um, and it's
important that we cover it somewhere
[snorts] right around this consent form.
Just a thought. Thank you.
and Denali.
>> Hi, I'm jumping on a little late today,
so I apologize for that. But the other
recommendation I want to make on
informed consent,
um it it would be great to include also
in here information about what's covered
and what is not covered. So people are
making um informed decisions related to
costs that might be an appropriate place
to also provide information about the
equity fund for those and and potential
eligibility or where to find um whether
[laughter] they're they might be
eligible for coverage. It'll be
important to lay out, you know, that um
parts of the psilocybin services will
not be covered by by insurance. And I
can dig up some um some model language
real quick.
Oh, let's see. And I see um Kate's hand
up again. Um and Kate, you can unmute.
Yeah, I mean considering that this is
the administration
day, is that what we're looking at? It
seems like we would have they would have
gone over that coverage options
thoroughly before getting to this point.
[snorts]
I don't know if there'd be more
questions at this point or you know that
would have been earlier.
I in my belief it would have been
earlier on the grounds that um
this is the least covered part of
the program. So maybe it's that maybe
it's notification
that administration
is not covered by insurance. They should
have been notified beforehand. However,
um right now the department is looking
at potentially
finding ways to get um maybe prep and
maybe integration covered. So, we'll
just give them the notification that
administration outright not covered by
insurance. Um
but yeah, they they would have been
discussing that hopefully
much before the day they show up.
Then I don't know if you had anything
else. I just started talking. I'm sorry.
>> I already muted myself. That's good.
>> Perfect. Then we'll go ahead and go to
dosage and administration.
So, psilocybin products must be
administered according to the
psychedelic therapist's guidance and
recommendation. Administration
procedures must include um the
verification of product identity and
dosage, confirmation that the product
was obtained through authorized
channels, documentation of the dosage
administered, observation of ingestion
or administration by the patient, and
patients must voluntarily
self-administer the product.
Facilitators must not course, pressure
or physically administer psilocybin to
patients.
questions, comments, concerns.
Katherine,
>> so I have a question. I don't know if
it's super relevant to this, but
are are we going to be allowed like So,
I usually updose. So, I start slow and
then I increase the amounts. Are we
going to be allowed to then order a
certain amount and if the the patient
doesn't want all of it, then we're going
to be returning it? That doesn't sound
right. Um, I guess I'm just kind of
curious like when we're keeping track,
obviously we should be keep track of
everything, but what's how much
flexibility do we have with respect to
dosage? Like sometimes clients, you
know, they think they're going to want
this amount, then you get in there,
you're recognizing they need a little
more or maybe they don't need as much as
they thought they needed. I just
wondering how that might work.
>> Yeah. So, I am very much on board with
umh I forget the word, but when you
break up a dose um and updose and
>> and do things like that um I'm very on
board for um very similar to what they
tell people with edibles, you know,
start low, go slow. Um because once
you've taken it, there's no going back.
And I have seen people that thought they
were so strong.
>> I know, right? [laughter]
>> And so I understand.
>> I've also seen people who think they
want like three and a half, but you give
them two and a half and they're like,
"No, I don't want anymore. I'm good."
And they are good. So,
>> yeah, that flexibility. So, I just want
to make sure that like when it talks
about verification and documentation, I
just wasn't sure and I again that may
not be relevant for this particular
point, but
>> I just wondering where we're talking
about that.
>> Yeah. You're a licensed therapist
though. No,
>> correct. Yes. So if you were a
psychedelic therapist, it would be
within your discretion to authorize a
dosage range and then the facilitator
would um say, "Okay, well, I got X
amount of dosage." And you obviously
would educate the facilitator and say,
"Okay, let's
>> start with this and let's build our way
up and see if we need this." Then um
>> you know, here's a whole package. Do
what you will with it. and
>> okay, you know,
>> and and Ian, sorry to interrupt, but
part of this is actually going to be uh
within the um the part of the rules,
which we're not on to that portion yet
with regard to approved locations
because there's going to have to be
security and things like that to be able
to keep whatever product uh you know,
whatever medicine has not been used. And
so that portion is going to be a part of
that. We had mentioned that previously,
but that was a part of the production
when we were doing the production rules
and so some people here weren't
necessarily on those. But it's a great
question, Katherine. It's one that's
come up several times about, well, what
happens if there's any excess product or
how do we handle it? And that's going to
be a part of that section of the rules,
which is after training and education.
So, [laughter]
>> thank you.
>> It's a great question and and really one
that we've been talking quite a bit
about.
>> Okay, great. as long as it's being
talked about somewhere. Thank you.
Appreciate it.
>> Yes, we would never open the package and
give it back. Hopefully not, but um
yeah, they'll work on that and get that
resolved. Um I do see James Brown.
>> Yeah. A couple questions that were
brought up um that I'm thinking about
right now is with dosage, are we still
thinking that three or 30 is kind of the
max dose? Is that where we're kind of
saying, you know, hey, we're going to
allow 30 milligrams or three grams? Uh
is that kind of still the number for the
dose that we're still kind of zeroing in
on for max dose or your thoughts on
that? We had discussed that prior.
I was under the impression that we
weren't going to set a hard cap.
>> Okay. So, we're not going to like in
Oregon, we max out at 50, let's say,
right?
>> And so, there's a hard there, but and
you know, with some of these people, as
we get the program running, we need to
kind of establish a potential max out, I
would say, 100% for safety. Um and
that's
>> the reason why we didn't want to was
just on the grounds of there are a lot
of commonly taken medications for um our
approved diseases, our approved
disorders that um
blunt the effects of psilocybin. And so
that was a large concern. We definitely
will up once we finish admin and
integration um talk more about dosage
and dosage for different um groups. We
just noted any dose I believe over 50
milligrams has to go through like um
special reporting requirements because
it's not an officially approved dose I
think is what we ended up leaning
toward.
>> Great. And then um [clears throat] with
that, you know, is there language that
says split dosing? You know, that's what
we kind of do is it to get the maybe the
launch or the chemical release that we
need um like you guys said for
comfortability. Sometimes we'll give
them an introduction dose, but then we
split that total dose into the two
doses. You know, I think again
literature shows splitting into two,
maybe not three or no more than
>> Yeah. So there's nothing in the program
to specifically
disinhibit splitting of doses. Um and I
do quite like the idea of a split dose.
I will raise the only part that
makes it difficult is that the 24 hours
when they cannot drive starts at the
last administered dose. So that would
every time you give a new one you
restart the clock. That's the only
objection I could see to it. But outside
of that, no, I agree. A split dose is
very necessary oftent times. And
especially when you're working with a
chemical that, you know, impacts two
people that look exactly the same in two
completely different ways. It is um
necessary, I would say, to you know,
taper up and updose and split doses and
and that kind of thing. So we can add it
um on our overall framework when we do
our you know specific cuz we still have
to go into like for the four conditions
that are already approved what doses are
best practices and which ones are more
um you know like experimental like we
just we are warning you that there are
excess risks and that kind of thing but
um yeah sorry I went on a tangent.
[snorts]
No. And then like with that, I'm 100%
with you. It's just I just wanted to
make sure we're discussing it. Um with
that dosing and the split dosing, um
what best practices that we've used, and
everybody's different in their practice,
um is is we kind of do it within the
first few hours. With that kinetics and
everything laying in, you're going to
know within the first two hours if they
need something else. And if they do, you
need to get it in there right away
because like you said, you don't want to
extend it too far versus giving it to
them at the six hour mark. you know just
best practice thought you know we try to
really give it upfront within that time
period but you know I just wanted to
discuss all that it's just great
discussion thank you
>> yeah and I I completely agree even if
you if you talk to people who use um
psilocybin recreationally they will tell
you and they'll be the first ones to
tell you like it is not worth it like if
you just trip to take psilocybin right
after you won't you wasted your
Um, so I've heard that from people. So I
would imagine that if we delay our um,
reup then we are wasting our money. The
tolerance has built up faster than we
provided um, additional
neurotransmitters.
But Denali had a question.
Yeah, I'm wondering if there might be an
opportunity and I don't I don't know how
I would make the edit recommendation,
but the self-administration
I think it I think it's good to default
to self- administration, but I worry
about especially our end of life um
patients and other patients who may have
physical disabilities that limit their
ability to self-administer and I I don't
want to exclude them. It's a really
important practice for us to protect
providers, but right, we have to find
that balance of protecting providers and
protecting patients and making sure
we're not excluding people with
disabilities that may make it hard or
impossible for them to self-administer.
Um, that being said, I don't have a
recommended edit. I I don't know if we
want to workshop it, but that's that
last bullet. So patients must voluntar
voluntarily self-administer.
What happens if somebody ha Yeah, I
guess I just want to anticipate what
happens if somebody has is not
physically able to because of a a
disability.
>> Do they have a caregiver?
>> That would be my
>> Yeah. Would the caregiver
>> then be allowed to because that person
is not the specifically psilocybin
regulated
person? Um,
and if they are already
used to providing medication, I don't
think that that would be too big of an
ask, but I think it would depend on each
situation. Uh, Dominic, maybe you had
better clarification.
>> I I actually do have two things. We
actually are over time right now and
we're going to have to close this on up.
So, these are great thoughts for uh for
the next meeting and to bring on up. Um
and it I think it because there is that
question as far as some of the language
moving it forward. James does have in
the chat about facilitators being able
to handle it and um yes, there is that
possibility as well. And uh and then
Ian, you bringing up the idea as far as
caregivers, that's also the other
portion. The biggest issue with it is
really just trying to ensure to help
protect people who have lentures and
trying to be able to do that. But I
think there's many paths um that can can
help with that. And I think the only
issue would be is if everybody who was
in the room had some sort of an a
different lensure outside of the
psilocybin program that there might be
those potential issues. And so that
again is part of what we need to
determine as far as how to language it.
And so Denali, yes, help with that
language and workshopping that would be
very helpful and appreciated. So, um,
but thank you everybody. I just sorry
that we're we're at that time. We have a
another meeting. We actually have to
jump on some of the some of the do
staff, but um yeah, I'll turn it back on
over to you, Ian.
Oh, did you freeze Ian or did I freeze?
>> Oh, there we go.
>> Oh, I was looking at my calendar trying
to find I was talking but I wasn't
unmuted. Um, so
we could push it right after
the on the 14th
at 9 to 10. Does that work for the
department?
>> July 14th.
>> Yeah,
>> it's a Tuesday. That's a Tuesday.
>> Yes.
I'm looking at the calendar here. Uh,
and yeah, July 14th would work.
>> Okay, so we will do July 14th at 9 to
10. Um, thank you everyone. I know we
didn't get to finish this document, but
we will definitely send it out for
further review until our next meeting.
Um, but thank you again for being here.
it is so much easier to not show up to
things than it is to show up. So, I
really do appreciate you taking time out
of your morning and especially on Monday
morning when it is hard to get up
anyway. Um, but again, thank you from
the bottom of my heart um to everyone
here and to everyone who has been
helping out to make this process real.
Um, the patients will surely appreciate
it.
>> And on behalf of the department, thank
you everybody. Great discussions this
morning.
>> Thank you.
>> Have a great day.